

Ramona Roller

Quantitative social scientist

H

15 December 1991



Weinbergstrasse 56/58, Switzerland



https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/people/rroller/



rroller@ethz.ch

About me -

Social scientist with a strong quantitative background. Fascinated by complex systems and their mathematical descriptions. Currently working on reconstruction methods for historical letter correspondence networks. Future aim: Develop spatio-temporal null models for historical letter correspondence networks.

Skill Python

Social network analysis

Socio-historical data analysis

Data visualisation

Agent-based modeling

(*)[The skill scale is from 0 (Fundamental Awareness) to 5 (Expert).]

Education

since 01/2018 Ph.D. candidate in data-driven modeling

of social systems

ETH Zurich, CH

• Develop quantitative statistical methods to analyse socio-

• Develop quantitative statistical methods to analyse sociohistorical data.

• Construct and visualise temporal network models.

• Expected graduation: June 2022.

09/2018 Participant at EPFL's Reproducibility in Computational Science

Summer School

Magliaso, Cl

 Acquired profound skills in writing reproducible research papers and data management. Specific tools include Git, R Shiny, and

Renga.

09/2015 - 12/2017 M.Sc. Computational Science

University of Amsterdam. NL

• Thesis: Optimising Resource Allocation in Socio-economic Systems with the Minority Game: A Case Study on Electric Cars in

Amsterdam.

06/2017 - 07/2017 Participant at SFI's Complex Systems Summer School Santa Fe

Institute, USA

Passed highly competitive world-wide application process.

• Deepened numerical and computational methods for the anal-

ysis of complex systems.

10/2011 - 07/2014 B.Sc. Psychology with Cognitive Science University of Sussex, UK

• Thesis: Differences between conscious and unconscious learn-

ing of social rules.

Research and Work Experience

11/2014 - 06/2015 Intern at Netherlands Organisation for

Applied Scientific Research (TNO)

Soesterberg, NL

• Developed a Linked Data model to cope with power cuts caused

by flooding.

• Applied qGIS to visualise power stations and water levels.

06/2013 - 06/2014

Junior research associate at Department of Informatics University of Sussex, UK

• Developed a novel method to quantify and visualise cognitive chunks based on the sequences of participants' drawings of elec-

trical circuit diagrams.

Publications

07/2021

 Roller, R, 2021: Vectorizing maps to generate geo-spatial data on territories of the Holy Roman Empire. socarxiv. doi=10.31235/osf.io/y9v68.

Conference attendances and research visits

09/2021 European Conference on Social Network Analysis (EUSN)(online)

Talk: 'Polarization in the 16th century: Ideologial groups dur-

ing the Reformation'.

• Access talk at https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/ramona_

roller/data/2021-09-08_EUSN. pdf

HNR conference (Historical Network Research) (online)

• Talk: 'Role detection in networks: Social differentiation during the Reformation'.

• Access talk at https://www.sg.ethz.ch/content/team/ Ramona_Roller/data/2021-07-01_HNR.pdf

	century network'. • Access talk at https://www.sg.ethz.ch/data/ 2021-04-15_HNR.pdf	
03/2021	Geography meets Digital Humanities: Neuere Ansätze raumbezogener Modellierung Erlangen (online), DE • Talk: 'Räumliche Aspekte der Konfessionalisierung: Vektorisierte Territorien des HRR erstellen und nutzen'. • Access talk at https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/ramona_roller/data/2020-03-12_Erlangen.pdf	
10/2020	Theorytellings Workshop der DHd AG Theorie Leipzig, DE • Talk: 'Warum wurde Luther protestantisch? Erklärungsnarra- tive mit statistischen Modellen entwickeln und zur Theoriebildung nutzen'. • Access talk at https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/ramona_ roller/data/2020-10-09_Leipzig.pdf	
09/2020	CUDAN Satellite at NetSci Rome (online), IT • Talk: 'Letter network to test theory'. • Access talk at https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/ramona_ roller/data/2020-09-11_Rome.pdf	
03/2020	Digital Humanities im deutschsprachigen Raum Paderborn, DE • Talk: 'Wie steuert geografische Distanz das Briefkorresponden- znetzwerk der Reformatoren? Eine Netzwerkanalyse'. • Access talk at https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/ramona_ roller/data/2020-03-05_Paderborn.pdf	
09/2019	European Conference on Social Network Analysis (EUSN) • Talk: 'Statistical inference for letter network of Reformation'. • Access talk at https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/ramona_roller/data/2019-09-11_Zurich.pdf	
07/2019	International Conference on Computational Social Science (IC ² S ²) • Talk: 'Network regression reveals factors driving the letter correspondence of 16th century reformers'. • Access talk at https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/ramona_roller/data/2019-07-18_Amsterdam.pdf	
06/2019	Research visit at Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities • Enlarged skills on vectorisation of raster maps and management of spatial data. • Talk: 'A workflow for automated vectorisation of raster maps'. • Access talk at https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/ramona_roller/data/2019-06-17_Vienna.pdf	
01/2019	Research Visit at Heidelberg Academy of Sciences and Humani-	

Talk: 'Das Briefkorrespondenznetzwerk der Reformatoren'.
Access talk at https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/ramona_

 $roller/data/2019-01-21_Heidelberg.~pdf$

Heidelberg, DE

HNR lunch lecture (Historical Network Research)

• Talk: 'Modeling Time in Interactions: Temporal paths in a 16th

04/2021

Organisation of scientific events

since 01/2021	Co-organiser of the workshop 'Opportunit	ies in computerised
	analyses of historical letter correspondence	es' Heidelberg, GER

- Teamed-up with project 'Theologenbriefwechsel im Südwesten des Reichs in der Frühen Neuzeit (1550-1620) led by Prof. Strohm in Heidelberg.
- Organised talks, discussion groups and accomodations for 30 participants.
- Speakers include international researchers from the humanities, computer- and data sciences.
- Planned date: Spring 2022

06/2018 Co-organiser and participant at Big Data in the Field Weekend Seminar

- · Organised talks, workshops, discussion rounds, and accommodation for 50 participants and 6 speakers.
- Speakers included German Data Science professors and representatives of German companies that apply Big Data-based technologies.

Awards

09/2020 Student grant for NetSci conference 01/2020

Travel grant for DHd conference (Digital Humanities im

deutschsprachigen Raum)

02/2012 - 12/2017 Member of German National Academic Foundation 07/2014

Stuart Sutherland Prize for an outstanding undergraduate dis-

sertation in psychology at the University of Sussex